Hi all, good evening.
I'm my audible guys, I'm audible and visible, good evening Sambet, thank you.
So what I'll do is I'll start my screen sharing, please confirm once you can see the screen.
Start the timer and then we'll have a conversation.
Can you again confirm guys if you can see the screen share? Thank you.
So let's have a five minutes timer.
Okay, great. So I see some of the people have joined the class, we'll wait for the other people.
Meanwhile, any doubts from your previous classes, previous class guys, like we had only one session.
Did anyone felt overwhelming the initial concept like how does internet work or what is full stack or it was okay, okay.
Any beginner who felt overwhelming like discussing all the big jargons initially.
Okay, I don't think anyone felt overwhelming, it was good enough.
Then, how was your day guys? Was it a long day? How was your day at office?
Bad, okay, I meant as bad as a beginner, it's good, perfect, please, as I was able to say, great, great, Maheshwar.
Yeah, I meant Kabir, how was it? What was it actually?
Even I had some tough day, I had planned releases that didn't go well.
I mean, I had an external dependency with other teams was still working on.
Good day, great, great, Sambit.
So how many of you were able to solve both the problems, assignments?
Give me thumbs up if you're able to solve, give me thumbs down if you're not able to solve or didn't attempt it.
Okay, I see one thumbs down.
Guys, please vote in again, like I'm asking it again since only nine people voted.
So can you give me thumbs up if you have solved assignments and if you haven't attempt or haven't touched it, give me thumbs down.
Okay, no worries Kabir.
Let's try to stay in, you know, keep it pace, like it will take only, I think, maximum half an hour of your time within two days of time.
So try to do it, possibly.
And I see other two people.
Guys who give thumbs down, any challenges you faced with content or you have any issues or you didn't get time, what was your problem?
If you want to, you know, message me personally, you can.
Okay, okay.
So try to, you know, do assignment problems.
If you're having any issues, let me know.
I can help it out.
I think one of the members have already pinged in the WhatsApp group.
The other team member has helped it.
So I face issue after installing Visual Studio Code and Windows machine.
Shant, can we pick your issue in the doubt session?
I'll help you out with that, whatever issues you are facing.
So one thing you can do is Shant is like as soon as you're facing issue, right, post it in WhatsApp group.
I might reply other whole like we have a bunch of people, right?
Group of people who are along with us are studying.
They'll also see that issue and help them out.
We'll help you out.
Okay.
Okay, okay, then Russian issues.
Please try to keep it up and close it down today or tomorrow whenever you have bandwidth.
Why semantic?
That part couldn't get much.
Okay, and I'll try to repeat that part.
Let's wait for another minute.
Then I'll get started.
Okay.
Meanwhile, I'll ask if you can see my screen share.
This is working fine, right?
Like you can see the iPad screen share.
Cool.
How much is necessary for the full stack model?
I was not able to complete this because of office work.
I'm still struggling to complete it.
I have a lot of backlogs currently.
Atul, I would suggest you one thing.
I'll take this last question, guys, for Atul or anyone who is having still DSA module pending, right?
It would be really difficult to travel in both the boards at a time now.
So DSA being a core element for, you know, cracking interviews.
I would say the most but post cracking interviews, you will be more spending time on doing what we are learning.
So keep this basics clear.
So all the basics that I'm teaching, please, you know, focus on this as of now, because this will build your knowledge on React and NodeJS.
If you're not able to focus or understand anything, if you have any doubt, do ask me.
But if these things are clear only, you will be able to learn.
So whoever having challenges from DSA or any other modules, I would ask you to know deep right eyes that one for now.
Because what I feel for my opinion is.
OK, if you have any personal things, we'll take it up in the doubt session again.
I'll talk more on that.
Hey, can anyone add or share around like WhatsApp group in the chat?
And OK, let's get started with class today, guys.
We are on time.
So.
OK.
OK, so let's let's get started with today's class.
You know, I'll try to put out the agenda.
First, what we'll be learning today.
So as the class name itself suggests, I will be learning two things.
Firstly, least.
Table and forms.
So in a whole web, the whole web context, like whenever you're developing a website or anything, these two things place really great amount of room like forms are the one of the difficult task to create or to delete.
OK, so people face many challenges.
I would ask you to know, be patient with me when we are learning.
We'll try to go deep.
I will understand each point.
OK, these three things will be covering it today.
Along with this, we'll be covering one of the topic is what are inline elements versus block elements.
So these are the four things that I plan to take it up.
Other than this thing, I'll take the doubts.
So one of the doubts that's been asked me asked to me is that, hey, why do this semantic elements were introduced?
OK, so to divide, you know, there are two things people generally use dev and span.
OK, so dev and span are the, you know, the user for dividing a sections or like you say that this is one of the area or this is one of the element or the one box or anything.
People have been using this before.
Even today, people use this elements itself more commonly, more specifically.
But when you say dev and span, right, whenever you are defining a box or anything, you don't know what this box is talking about or what this content or what is this HTML is written for until unless you have yourself written it.
Someone is reading the code.
He cannot understand it.
OK, audio is coming.
Let me check this.
Give me a second.
I'm audible better now.
Anandu.
OK, great.
So before HTML 5, they've been using only two things like to divide the sections or write content dev and span.
But later on in HTML 5, people have introduced more elements which are name specific.
When I say name specific, what do I exactly mean?
You can all you can do all the things that you can do with semantic tags using dev and span.
But to understand HTML to make it more readable or cleaner code, they introduce semantic like elements.
Like if I write down a few things like header element or footer element, OK, main tag, then section tag.
OK, then button you have.
Right, you have now.
So these whenever I write the things right, whenever I'm writing this thing by definition itself, we know that we are talking about something we are able to relate it.
But when I say that this div is also acting, this is for acting for head and this the second div is acting for footer.
We don't know until unless we have written the code, the person the other person is coming and trying to read this using devs.
It's difficult to understand.
So semantic tags are more preferred.
If you are able to write it, it makes your HTML more readable.
Is that clear is why semantics should have been introduced or how they can help us out.
OK, great.
So let's get started with today's content, which is least.
OK, now, so basically in HTML, we have, you know, three types of least guys like least.
If you see wherever you go for like you open a word pad or any doc Google Docs now representing navigation and tab Suresh like pains you have navigation like top menus.
Like on the like I'll show you how navigation can be used.
OK, you can say navigation panel generally.
Multiple buttons.
OK, so coming back to least guys, how many of you have used this list?
Like if you go for, you know, you make a to do list, you make your noting them down, you note them down using 1234 or use ABC or you define bullet points or you use some sort of, you know, representation.
So everyone might have came across the least right.
You might be doing it in your any doc or to do app or any Google Doc.
Right. Have anyone have hope all you have used this list right now.
We'll see how they have been actually used.
OK, how they have been defined or how they can be created.
OK, so in least in HTML, right, you have basically three things.
OK, one is unordered least.
OK, second thing we have is ordered least.
Third thing we have is description list.
OK, we'll see them one by one example.
Let's directly go and code it down.
OK, let's see and code it down.
I hope all of the members except the one I see who are facing challenge with results record.
Everyone have installed it.
Whoever have installed right, one can code along with me whenever I'm typing it down for better hands on anything you learn.
Whatever I'm saying, if you understand that wouldn't be enough.
If you code along with me, that would be really helpful.
OK, guys, let's say we introduce class to inside this.
I'll create least dot HTML.
Again, I'm using Emmet, guys, HTML 5.
Then once I have this, I'll name this as a least.
OK, now let's say if you go with like unordered list, right, unordered lists are generally used whenever you don't have specific definition like or like you have a sequence of.
Whenever you don't have prioritized list like it's just a general list of items that you write down.
OK, can anyone give me when unordered list can be used?
Any idea like when unordered list can be used?
Any any idea when unordered list can be used?
Or you have seen cart items?
OK, so anything else, guys, like.
Any any any else anything else like who doesn't have any, you know, representation.
Grocery list or something which is whichever doesn't have any priority or the right at that particular places we can use unordered list.
Let's see how you can write it down.
So, you know, there's only one thing like if you want to define the list, if you are using unordered list, you have to remember UL.
UL stands for unordered list.
OK, once the tag is opening, I'll also close this unordered list tag.
Once I have closed for each list item, you have to define it specifically.
OK, this is how you define a list item.
Let's say we are building a list of like let's say grocery items people have suggested.
OK, now let's say if you are building groceries.
Now, let's say you are trying to build on the list of items that you want to buy at the start of month.
Like recently, many people who are running their homes might have, you know, your parents might have made you to write down the list of things or, you know, add into the cart.
If someone is doing BlinkIt or like any other app or you might have picked it up from the store.
Right. So let's say let's let's let's write down something, guys, in the comments, like what what all things you want to add and see this one.
Let's say I add it. I start with maybe rice, five kgs that is needed for home to run a month with three people living.
Let's say oil of.
Two liters.
OK, then you have a wheat.
It may be again five kgs. Let's make it 10 kgs.
And let's say you have tea.
Right. 500 grams.
And coffee for sure.
So now let's see how this these things are represented in order unordered.
So what I'll do is I've earlier I've shown you one of the ways using live server or secondary.
Second thing is opening directly, you know, using the file system.
The third thing that I want to show is like using directly that I have.
I have installed one extension which which in behind the scene uses live server so that I don't need to switch between tabs of Chrome and, you know, editor.
So I kept this way.
OK, so this extension, you can use it directly from your extensions list.
I'll show you.
HTML preview.
If you are practicing practicing any time right, you can see this live preview.
So you can install this live preview like I'll also copy this and keep it for you guys.
OK, I'll I'll put it in the like, yeah, scalar editor, you can say.
So it's it's so if you're practicing any time HTML.
Not exactly sure somebody if this if they're using the same thing.
But this is something related same same way, like where you are typing it done parallely.
It reloads the website.
You don't need to again open the browser.
OK, now let's let's get started.
Now, if you see this coming back to this another list, guys, now anything that you define it by default, you are seeing in the bullet points.
Now, if you go for another list, you have seen many ways of representing, right?
You might have circles or the squares.
If you know, if you remember.
Like if I write down, so if you want to enhance any attributes, sorry, any elements you type down, you write down many attributes.
Let's say if I add one and one of the attributes like type and define like, hey, I want maybe square.
Let's say represent this bullet points in square.
So when I make it square, you can see this.
It's represented in square.
I hope this it's visible.
Right.
This is zoom length works or.
OK, so so you can always represent in many things like one element.
So you can always represent in many things like one or either circle.
OK, or circle is gives circle is something which when you define the circle, it's empty circle, guys.
So by default, if you give a default, it is circle with filled.
You know, it's filled.
It's not an empty.
OK, so generally you have three values when you go for type attribute.
Like you can define bullet points and square squares or you can use circle or you can use the chain.
Minimize this default.
So when you use default, it is an empty or if you sorry by default, this is how you represent the circle.
Then this square.
OK, I hope everyone is clear.
With this unordered list.
Guys, any doubts till now?
All right.
Now, let's get started with something other thing, which is ordered list.
Now, let's say that you have a sequence of things that you want to do.
What would be the activity where you want to do a sequence of things?
Like where how do you do it?
Like let's say you have a to do list, right?
A basic to do list.
Let's say let's build our to do list.
OK.
Ordered list.
Let's have one of the flights from less to high daily routine.
Yeah, I was talking about daily routine.
Like when you wake up, what are the things that you do or the next event you do that?
That's all basic difference, right?
Whenever you represent something in order list, let's say.
To do list.
Daily events.
People have a habit of writing it down, right?
Many people don't want to remember things like what are the sequence of things.
They write it down so that like they'll follow that thing, whatever they have written.
So it's one of my habit that I keep on doing multiple things at a time.
So I write down things so that I remember what I have to do back, go back and check.
So I make a notes of one thing.
So that's how order list comes into the role for me.
As Kiran suggested, even recipe, right?
You need to add if you want to cook a Maggi, you cannot put the Maggi or then water.
It goes like water, then Maggi, then masala, right?
So same way, like it's a sequence order.
So when you go for order list, let's say I want to define daily events.
So one of the basic event is let's say what we have been taught in school, right?
Whenever you wake up, firstly, you thank the God for the day, right?
Pray for your life or pray for the good life that God has given you.
Or get your day started with prayer, let's say.
So I'm saying that prayer, OK, first thing, first event of the day.
Then second event could be brush the teeth.
Then maybe you have a list of events which you can say getting ready.
Getting ready involves everything, guys.
Let's define it that way.
Then let's say you have office.
Then let's say you have an assignments to solve.
OK.
Maybe then you have class.
OK, then maybe you have family time.
Then you can have sleep time or you can say bedtime.
This is on a top level, right?
How our day looks like.
Generally, I've outlined how your day might look like when you're a scalar student along with when you're a working employee, right?
Do you guys agree, guys?
Everyone?
Do you guys agree?
Great, guys.
So now, what's the difference in the order list versus an order?
Now, in order list, if you see, you have a series of events, right?
One, two, three, four, five, six, seven.
The numbers are coming for the order list.
Now, what if I want to change this type of format?
If you remember, there have been something like, you know, Roman way of representation.
If you see in childhood, right?
In childhood, like we have like context, right?
Whenever you pick any subject book, wherever you have table of context, like all the chapters or anything,
they used to represent with Roman letters like first chapter, second chapter, third chapter for the math books specifically.
Does anyone remember it?
Or everyone left the school back five years, 10 years back.
Right.
So let's try out that way.
Now, even now, if I want to enhance this order list, order list element, right?
I'll again use a new attribute, the same attribute that I use.
Now, if you see the amount of things like whatever things that I can put it here.
Now, I was talking about using Roman description.
So let's say I give it capital I.
So if you see, I'm getting this Roman numbers, one, two, three, four, five, six.
If I want it to be in small, I can give it in small.
OK.
Similarly, if I want to give it in alphabets, I can give small abc.
And also I can make it capital, which will give me capital A to H.
OK.
So if I write down what all attributes it can take, let's say the type attribute for the order list, it can take capital A, small a, then capital I, which starts for Roman, you know, numbering, then small i.
Then by default, you have numbers.
OK.
So everyone can play around with this.
There's nothing much inside order list, I would say, because both follow the same concepts.
You have to define each list item under the li tag, which stands for li list.
And if you want to go with order, just remember O goes with order, U goes with unordered.
OK.
So any doubts in this case with ordered and unordered?
It's pretty simple straightforward, isn't it?
So somebody says, no, somebody with any challenge to have clear, right?
OK, great, great guys.
So now the third type of list that I've told you now, if you remember, like I want to give you one example, think of like a restaurant.
Let's go back to the restaurant.
If you go for menu, how does menu stands by like they put up one section, they put one section like starters under that one section, you have list of items.
Again, you go for main menu, you have list of items.
So it's it's it's comparatively different from ordered and unordered.
Right.
Intentation.
Yeah.
Yeah, that's how it happens.
Right.
Let's compare.
We cannot build that same thing using ordered and unordered list simply.
Right.
Do you guys agree if you want to build a menu or a card that you see menu card like which have a section like a starter section under you have list of items under menu, you have a list of items.
So now let's see if you want to build that how we can go with.
Now, if you want to build such kind of things right, then we have something like description list.
OK.
Let's say.
I define it as description list.
OK.
Which stands for deal.
Now.
I'll give deal tag.
Once I have description list.
Now, after that, you have another thing.
This is a very people don't really use them as as much, but they have different things have written wrapper over it.
But I want to define it for you guys.
So then you have description term or you can say category.
Actually, if it's a category status or anything, let's say I define it as starters.
OK.
Then this goes for DT.
Then let's say you have another thing.
Once you have defined description term, then you have description like.
Describe the items under it.
OK.
So this thing goes for DD.
Generally, when said when they say it is a description of a description term.
OK.
All the descriptions of multiple descriptions.
Let's say if you want to define this one, first thing that you should go is like, let's say define the table like description term.
Let's say I again go with the starters here.
If you see.
I'm able to whenever say we in temptation, it's starts with complete left right categorization like it starts with left.
Then under that you have some cat items coming in the right.
Now, let's see if that that is what it is being followed here.
Now, when I go for a DD, which is describing what all things come under starters, does anyone want to give what all things you see generally in menu for the status case?
I like my favorite one.
Manchurian.
How many of you write like Manchurian?
Chili paneer.
Nice.
Or.
Dragon chicken.
OK.
Again, chicken lollipop.
No, so let's say let's keep it this way.
Starters are some words like this amount of things.
Now, if you can, are you able to relate this with a menu item like this is how it looks like.
And you have a one section under that you get a new section.
Now, let's say we define another new section, which could be.
New section could be main menu.
OK.
Let's say I say that.
How you define main menu as main course, right?
Generally, when we go into buffet system, they define it main menu as a main course.
Now, let's say what you want to keep it in main course under rotis only you have four or five rotis.
So let's say I define it as common as all the rotis.
You under this, you get a room Ali.
Then you can have Parota.
OK.
Multiple things, right?
Then let's say also you have.
Biryani, right?
Let's say I define it again.
Multiple biryani's here.
Could be chicken.
Could be paneer.
Then you have multiple curries like could be a chicken curry.
I'm just giving them a broader description in chicken only.
They don't have 10 dishes in paneer.
They'll have 10 dishes.
Right.
So this is how your main course looks like.
Now, let's say if you one thing which is which is left to in the menu is like deserts, which is the end part.
Isn't it?
Now.
New section.
Deserts.
Any suggestions for deserts?
Gulab jamun.
How many of you like Gulab jamun?
Who are the desert fans?
Okay.
Great.
So let's say I define.
Oh, too many.
Gulab jamun.
Let's say ice cream.
Then rasmalai.
So I'm using, you know, more watery.
Because I like rasmalai too much.
I only like that thing.
In childhood we used to have a sweet shop.
So I use it left eating all those things.
Follow the.
So in general we are halvaiz from future generations.
I want to serve the stomach.
Brownie.
So, OK.
I think this is enough.
So I hope now you got the basic difference.
So I think this is enough.
Like seeing this example.
When to go for description list.
When to go for ordered list.
When to go for unordered list.
And how you can type.
Really basic guys.
Any type of list you have a wrapper.
Whatever type of wrapper is that you have only three wrappers.
Order, unorder and description.
Once you define the wrapper.
For order and order.
You can directly define whatever items you have.
It will take by default.
Like it will have default style.
If you want specific to change it.
You can use type attribute and you can change it.
When it comes to description list.
Since it's a menu sort of thing.
You have to give a category name first.
Once you define a category name using description term.
Then you can define using description items.
Or description of description term.
So it goes for DD.
Now under this DD.
You can define multiple items.
This way.
So any doubts guys.
With list items.
Or you are confident about that.
If someone asks you to define design list items.
You will be able to do it.
Do you have any type for descriptions?
I didn't explore it.
Let's explore this.
Type.
I don't think we have anything guys.
Never used it.
Let's say I used one here.
Nothing will affect.
Okay.
Or let's say I give circle also.
It won't come.
So description list works this way.
It's a header.
Under one header.
It will have multiple things.
So in DL right.
If you go for.
Under DL tag.
I didn't explore anything.
DL element.
HTML.
There is nothing.
As such I guess.
Even.
W3 schools haven't defined anything.
Let's say if you go for MD and docs.
See.
No one is using any attribute for a DL.
That's how it works guys.
I don't think anyone have anything specifically.
Can we use nested list?
Surely you can use.
Like let's say.
Let's convert this thing.
How we can convert this one.
I will give you an example.
Let's say we are building again.
List of items right.
Now.
Let's say I start.
Order list.
Inside that you have one li.
Inside this li.
What if I.
Leave this list of items.
Let's say.
Okay.
Again the second thing.
I will again copy this one.
Just let me copy this again.
Now let's.
I don't need tab 9.
Now if you see.
Under order list I have copied two things.
Like I have made two list items.
Which are coming by section 1 and section 2.
Okay 1 and 2.
This is fine.
Let's see.
That you can use nested things.
Okay.
Great.
Let's say I make another.
This one I.
Give us.
Third section for better view.
Okay.
Alright.
Let me remove.
This section from here.
Deserts.
So now.
If you want.
Since we don't have title.
If you want since we don't have type operator.
Now you can see that for each section.
I have also given numbering system.
So one as status two as a main course.
Third as a desert.
How did I was able to do it.
Like I used.
Ordered list.
And inside that each list item.
I have used this dldi description.
And then I have defined category.
Then I use like items.
This is fine guys.
So give me thumbs up guys.
If you can go ahead with the table.
Because this is one of the easiest topic.
That we could have considered today.
We have much more interesting things to learn today.
Okay. Cool.
So at least few more guys.
Few more thumbs up. We have too many people in the class.
At least 10 to 15 would really helpful.
Okay. Didn't get that numbering part.
Give me a minute.
So.
Somewhere I got the question from this is that.
Can you combine.
Two types of list.
Okay. So what I said that.
Hey you can do that.
What I did is. Now if you see.
Earlier whatever description list is.
Doesn't have any numbering format.
And we didn't have any type attribute.
To make it a numbering format.
So what I did is.
I created ordered list.
Which will give me numbers.
Now inside each list item.
I will add. So DL element.
Which will give me a separate section.
Okay. Same thing I have repeated multiple times.
Like let's say three items.
Which will give me three numbers.
Clear.
Chalo guys.
Next topic would be.
Tables.
Table start HTML.
Let's close this one.
HTML5.
Alright.
Let's open the preview.
Show preview.
Okay.
Let's say this is.
Tables.
Now.
Tables is an another.
You know interesting.
Use case where you see.
Too many things are represented.
In terms of tables right.
Can you guys give me an example.
Like where you see tables.
One thing that I would say.
If you go for your pay slip right.
One who awaits to see.
How many tax it got deducted.
Or how much you got paid.
So if you go.
You have multiple sections divided.
With each section.
And you see the divisions right.
And attendance.
And even like there are too many examples.
Like if I give you some examples.
That I wrote personally.
Schedules.
Schedules right.
Even PSP percentage and scaler.
Everything is represented in terms of table right.
Calendar.
Even IMDB.
Bill invoice right.
All those things are represented.
In terms of table.
So table is also one of the interesting.
Way to like represent how you can represent.
The data in terms of rows and columns.
Because whenever you see table.
It's like a 2D matrix isn't it.
Now let's see how you can define.
A data in terms of.
Like these two sections.
Okay.
Now.
Firstly.
Table generally you know.
If you go for any table right.
Basically you have two things.
By default.
Let's say you have this thing.
Table element.
If you want to define a table.
You have to start with the table attribute.
That itself stands for that.
Let's say if I have table.
Now.
This is how you start with writing with a table.
Now inside the table what are the sections.
That you generally see guys.
What are the sections you remember.
Let's say you take an example of.
The scaler percentage itself.
Rows and columns.
That's fine.
But let's say.
PSP percentage.
That's something that you see right.
I don't exactly know.
How it is represented.
But let's say there would be a batch name.
There would be a person name.
There would be a PSP percentage and their rank right.
Let's say if we have such way.
Now.
By this we know that each table.
Will have its header isn't it.
Table will have a header.
Which will give the.
What are the column names.
Isn't it. Like serial number.
Name. Grad. Year. PSP.
Ok guys.
These are the header names. Now let's say.
If you want to define any header right.
By default you have something like.
Table header if you have to define.
There is a tier.
Called T header.
Which stands for table header items.
Now let's say if you are defining a table header.
Let's say I will go and say that.
Hey give me a T head.
Once I have T head.
Now inside T head also.
You have to always create.
A row. Inside that you have to create.
Multiple columns.
Now for creating rows.
Ok.
For creating rows right.
There is a one tag called table rows.
If you go with table rows.
That is defined by TR.
Ok. Now.
First I will create a TR.
Table row. Inside that I will say that.
Hey I will create.
TH.
Now each column.
Either it is.
Ok. Now I will say.
Let's say.
Each column.
Can be defined using two tags.
TH or TD.
TH is something.
When you go for heading part.
Ok. TH goes for.
Table heading.
Under that section.
So all the headings like table headings.
Now let me minimize this.
Now again.
TD goes for.
Table data.
Ok.
So I am writing descriptions here.
Such that once you refer the notes right.
You will be able to see why I am defined this thing this way.
And what it is standing for.
Ok. Now.
As you people suggested me.
There are the four things that can exist right.
Let's say serial number. Ok.
Now let's say.
Second thing we have.
Let's say.
You suggested me.
Instead of grid.
Instead of serial number.
Let's say we have name. Which is a unique attribute in itself.
Then you have subject.
I am giving very simple guys.
In order to teach it. Let's not get complicated.
Let's say we have a PSP.
Fine.
Name of a person.
Subject and its PSP.
Now if you see.
Whenever you are defining in TH.
Whenever you use this right.
For the table heading.
This thing will. The table headings will come in like.
You know bold format.
Now let's define.
Content for it.
Now whenever you go for content right.
You have to use.
A tag called table body.
T body.
Inside t body itself.
You will be able to define.
Throws.
Now again.
If you want to define a row.
Just create a new row.
Once you create a new row.
Again you create a TDA element.
Which is going for data.
Like for this data.
Will be aligned exactly with the first.
TD will take it a space for the TH.
Which is name.
Now let's say if I am giving a name as Tejal.
Okay.
Once I have Tejal.
Again I go with TD.
Now let's say I go for DSA.
Let's say.
Is 80%.
Okay.
PSP.
So this is how you can define.
Table head and table body.
At least till now.
Anyone facing any challenge.
Understanding wise.
Pretty much clear or how you are facing it.
How you are feeling it guys.
Okay.
So now.
Let's say I also define this T body.
Goes for.
Table content wrapper.
Similarly what I will do is.
I will create multiple columns.
Multiple rows.
Let's say I have 4.
With Muneshwara.
Okay.
Let's say let's make it 85.
Let's make another.
Kabir.
Don't take anyone personally guys.
I am giving some random numbers.
Okay.
Or else I will change the subject.
Let's say LLD.
Okay.
Computer fundamentals.
Now let's say.
Again.
Let me get another name.
Shant.
Okay.
Let's say same.
Now if you guys see this.
Let's give this a 75.
Let's make.
Let's keep this.
Okay.
Now.
What we are seeing by this is like.
Like what we have defined till now.
Is that we created headers.
And for that we filled this data.
Now this table.
Each table will have a set of.
Let's say I am using one of the attribute guys.
You need not to worry with this attribute.
I will teach them.
Once we go for CSS part.
If you see as soon as I write border.
You can see a border was added.
I will use one pixel.
Solid.
Black.
Need not to worry about this thing.
Even if I don't write.
It will take it as this border.
Now along with that.
I will use.
Let it be this way till now.
Border.
You will clear Shant.
You will clear many great interviews.
Just be focused.
Just keep doing it.
There will be a day.
Now you will feel proud of yourself.
Now.
Till now guys any challenge.
With understanding basic things.
Anyone having any challenge.
With understanding table basics.
Like table header or table row.
Or how you define column.
Please participate guys.
I have seen only 2-3 people.
Clear.
Now.
Let's say.
There are 2 things now.
Let's say I define one thing.
Under the table body also.
What if I want to define something like.
Footer.
So under.
Here on this also.
You have something like table footer for the tape.
Like I am having problem nested.
Can you explain show once again.
I will do it in a minute.
I will pick it up that nested.
I will show it back again.
Let's focus on this.
Once this is cleared I will go back there.
Works Ashish.
Now.
For the table also I can show.
Footer.
For the footer.
What I am showing is just a summary.
Or else I will say that.
Total average.
What would be average guys?
Out of this.
Can anyone get me an average.
Of this course.
80, 85.
80, 75.
So you can calculate it.
80.
Plus 85.
Plus 80.
Plus 75.
Divided by 4.
It gives me 80.
Great. Thank you.
Thank you Sean.
Let's say 80.
Now.
I didn't get T foot added here.
Let me see why it didn't come up.
So firstly I have only one row.
Inside that row I should have.
TD.
Because the description that is total average.
Once I have this is also TD.
Because it's talking about percentage.
Now.
Let's keep back again.
So do you think guys this is the right way of representation?
Do you think this total
average is the right way of representation?
Like what can we make it?
Like to make it look better.
Any ideas like what we can
look from look wise right?
What if we can extend
this right?
Total average till here and
merging the columns right?
Moving this 80 to this end
and total average merge
like column 1 and column 2.
Right?
Let's try that. So whenever
you want to extend right?
One particular like item.
To multiple columns.
Like you want to extend multiple
columns. Then something that you
can do is that you can say
row span.
Now when I'm saying row span.
I'm talking about how many
rows I mean columns
that it should cover. Sorry.
Call span.
So I'm talking about
how many columns this total average should cover.
Now when I say that
I want to cover this name and subject.
I mean to say that I'll pass a value
of 2 here. Which will
say that I'm covering 2 parts.
So I merged
2 columns into 1 and I've told
that hey total average take
this whole space.
Is call span clear guys?
How call span can be used?
Let me write down here
for better idea.
Call span.
Which defines
amount of columns.
It need to cover
or spread across.
Similarly there is another
thing guys. There is another thing. What if
let's say Teja has
another subject. Like let's say
Teja has another subject of
can say
LLD.
And let's say Teja scored
in LLD let's say 75.
And let's say there
is something again.
Let's say he have also
another subject which is computer
fundamentals.
Okay.
Let's say he again scored
inside computer fundamentals and he scored 83.
Okay.
Now. Again
do you think
here again we can make some
changes. We merged columns earlier.
Now we say that we are talking
about Tejal here.
And Tejal's name is being repeated thrice.
What if we can merge
3 of rows for the name and keep
DSA LLD fundamentals
separately.
Right. Let's try
that one. How we can do it.
Now whenever you
are going for this one. Right. Let's say I
go and tell that
I'll say that
earlier we use something called as call
span. Now I'll use row span.
I'll say that 3 names. Okay.
Now if you see as soon as
I gave this
everything got disintegrated.
Like everything looks odd.
Now to fix this one what I'll do is
like I'll remove this name. Okay.
I don't need this name firstly.
Now if you see
if second row and third row
are having only 2 items.
First column is
being spread by this name for the
3 levels. Like 3 levels
Tejal has been filled. Now I'm only
using 2 things to be filled.
Okay. Which is like
second column and third column.
Are you able to relate like how row span
will work?
Let's draw
Okay. Got it. Right. Cool.
So if anyone having any challenge
I can explain. Right. What exactly happened
is once we filled this first column
in the second column when I'm coming
I'm seeing that first column is already
taken. So I
define only for second and third.
That's how it works. So I
hope now row span is also
clear. But I'll write down this thing here.
So that next time whenever you
come it should be clear for you.
Let me
copy this.
Just
I need to update this as rows.
Okay.
I hope
everything is clear now as of now.
But one thing is missing guys.
Footer part. Yeah.
Scroll down a bit.
One thing is missing guys.
How is it taking second instead
on the first.
You mean to say here
like I didn't exactly
get your question Kabir.
Are you talking about
why this
LLD is taking in the second part
instead of first
for Tejan.
Right. Now. So let's say
I defined it one item
which will take three parts of space.
Okay.
I've told that hey in the head part
I'm having only three headers.
Name, subject and PSP.
Now I told that hey Tejal
name will be taken for the first
three spaces. Now when I say three spaces
it is already
when I'm defining a second row the
first it is already defined.
So whenever I define the first thing
it will go for the second place.
For the same thing
for the third place.
Yeah. Okay.
So it is already specified because headers are constant.
Clear.
So somebody was asking
me to go to the footer part.
So
now guys anything is anything missing
like we are
saying this table we are having names,
subject, PSP all great.
We have used row, span, column,
span and defined headers
and all the things. But
is there something missing?
Anything missing? I tried footer
it came at top. Okay.
Did you?
I'll check with you Pindra once like in
doubt session. Let's pick it up that way. Okay.
Least table name. Yeah.
Tejal mentioned table name.
What this table is talking about?
If someone new person comes
who is not from computer
science background or
not from scalar, he would not
get the what PSP or what is this
TSA or LLD right?
Do you guys agree?
There should be a context what this table is
talking about. Isn't it?
So now if you want to define
a table name anytime right
you have one thing
like you can use caption.
Whenever you define caption right
you mean to say that you are talking about
like what this table
is talking about in general. Let's say I
define it as a tracking
of subjects
or let's say
student
scores
or like something like
okay any
name but in general what my idea was
like how you can add a
caption to it.
I hope this is clear guys.
How this thing works. Table works.
Okay.
Any doubts from the
context of like
you know till now whatever
we have discussed. If anyone is not
able to follow up or having any
issues I will pick it up. I will pick it up
in doubt session. I will ask you to
change and I will check that. No issues with that
but generally if you have anything
do let me know.
Can the footer be kept bold or to
achieve that we have to add
no no not needed.
If you want to keep a bold right
always you can do something like let's say
I'll have a style tag
don't use it. Don't be worried about this one.
We'll learn all the things okay.
Okay.
Then also you can use
font.
So you can use a style tag
and define what type of things that you want.
How it is merging.
Combining the row I had doubt.
Okay. Now
so
coming back to Vigneshwar
Vigneshwar
Can we add a
list of subjects in a table call.
Give me a second guys. I'll take
Vigneshwar's question first.
So Vigneshwar now I'll
try to re-explain how this row has been
combined. Earlier right we had
three places like three subjects
under the Tejal name DSA, LLD and
Computer Fundament. I thought like
why we not combine all the rows
and use only one Tejal name. Right.
So what did I do is that I have
in the first row where Tejal was there
I have told that hey take this
name and spread it till
three rows. Okay. I said
spread it till three rows. Now whatever
next three rows are there under that
Tejal will be automatically added.
Okay. Then
what I did in second row is like
I've added a LLD part
like I didn't have that first
TD because it is already occupied
till the third row.
Okay. If you see this only three rows
first row and only defined I
have spreaded this one and merged
completely. I haven't
defined in second row and third row because it is already
consumed by first row.
Is that clear Vigneshwar?
And also I had
can we add a list of subjects in table column?
List of
subjects.
We can do that. We can do that.
Let's say
it's a combination of HTML.
How do you want to define? Let's say in this
TD I have again
unordered list. Okay.
If you see in unordered list let's say I have
list item
inside that I write dsa
again I can have
right.
So you can write all the combination guys.
Whatever combinations you need you can write down.
So I'll keep it simple as of now.
If you have any
challenges trying out
combining things
we'll discuss this later.
So I hope tables
and list are clear guys.
So someone was asking me related to
combination of list.
How that list combination
worked?
Who was it?
Ashish.
So if you see this Ashish
what did I do here?
I think the rest equation me.
Like if you can combine ordered
and description list or any combination
of list. So what did I do?
Generally I went
and ordered list which are like one,
two, three. Inside ordered list
you define each item under the list tag
li tag right. I've had the simple
li tag. Now inside
each li tag again I open
dl tags. Now if you see
under dl tag I've described starters
and under that I've given each list
of item separately. Now
I went with the second list of item.
Again I started dl tag.
Inside that I've defined another course
and I've given its subsections.
Is this clear? Because why did I explain
this example this way is because we didn't have
ability to add
a type attribute to
dl tag.
Because type is not supported
but if you want to add numbering convention
this is how you can do it.
So I hope guys this is clear.
So I want
to get started with forms.
Thank you for
communicating
replying me
for the chats.
Now
guys please stop chatting
please focus here.
Hope you can see ipad guys everyone.
We are starting with
html forms.
So if we cover the topics well
we'll leave early or else
we'll cover more on portfolio
project. It's up to you whatever you choose.
Anyways I'll share the
code base with you. It's out of the curriculum.
I'm giving you but if you want me to cover
I'll cover that. But it's up to you. Please
focus so that we can cover that part.
Now
forms
Now whenever
where all you can
see the forms generally.
Where all you can see the forms.
Give me broader scope like what
amount of forms that you have seen in general
life like in day to day
life.
Login
Give me few more things.
Sign up
Registration
Let's keep it this way
till this example.
We have these three things.
These three things can extend
up to anything but let's keep it
these three things.
If you go for login
what all things are there?
What all things are there in login?
What type of things are there?
Let's say you go for a page
let's say you define it
login. What all things
do you ask?
Ok
username
let's say this is
this is password
and
captcha
does anyone
remember me?
like forgot
password that's cool
I'll add this as a remember me
ok
then you have something like
login
Now
let's see how's
general behavior like what you have observed
now if I type in this
thing
what I'm able to like
if I'm able to type into the username
can you see it when you're typing it?
when you're typing it
your username you can see right
so can we say this is of type
text
right
when you type down in the
password
can you see password?
or you see dot dot dot dot
no right so this is of different
type this is of different
type let's say I don't want to define
what is the type of it but this is of
different type
ok but there is something
happening that user is not able to see
right similarly
remember me is something
like where you get a tick mark isn't it?
you get a tick mark whenever you
check mark or you have
something like right
now what that thing is called
anyone know or does anyone know what
it is called checkbox right
now
I want you to
give me what all things like let's say
you go for registration right
as you say in this this is a text
now this different type is generally
we call it as a password type
right so
we have defined
or like let's say we define few things
you have text
you have password
you have checkbox
you have this
button
and what all things you can think of
like what all things different type of things
can be needed let's say you go for
registration you go for gender part
select your gender
male female or other
what type of things can come radio button
right
okay
someone might be asked to like
drop down
great
and what all things
that you can see
I agree with small tick
that's a checkbox Suresh
or let's say
someone ask you
about like
feedback box or like let's say
write about yourself
yeah Rohit says
text area
if someone doesn't know
understand different text and text area
I will cover it up okay description part
now and what all
things you can think of guys
I have few more things
whenever you are creating gmail
you are supposed to
select your email
also
date of birth
okay next next guys
anything else anything else
drop down goes with select
phone number
email right email
phone
address address
will be again used for text area
something
mandatory fields right
now but think of something else one thing
your guys are missing one thing if someone
guesses it it's really great
one thing you are missing
I will give an example where you can think of
now you ordered something through swiggy
it reached it but you didn't like
it's not what you expected
now you go to health channel and you do something
upload right great
this is a file upload
so
these are the common generic
things right these are the type of things that you
handle in form ratings
right that's a
rating itself
it's a one LLD equation
how do you design ratings
okay we will come to that
but later on pop up that's a overlay
that's not a form okay sure
but these are the least
of things that you generally see on a form right
these are the least of things type of things that
you see on a form wherever
you go so why we say forms
are difficult is because
the way the data is hold or the type
the things that is needed to you know
handle this one
is difficult let's see
how we can do this one
we will pick it up by simple login
form then we will go with the
registration which is a bit difficult part
we will define each one step by step
now let me go back
to the editor
and let me
open this
forms.html
HTML5
let's say a form
let's say this as a
login form rename it as login form
login form
now
let me open this preview
show preview
okay fine
now so
let's say I write down
as a header to
login form
okay
now
anything guys
as of now
as of now anything that you see
as like table is wrapped
under the table like similarly
if you want to do something for the
like you know form it should be
wrapped under the forms thing
okay now let's say
first thing that you have to do is
like it should open and close the form
okay
this is a base element
which lets you to create a form
okay everything should be inside this form tag
now
to handle all the types of attributes
that you just told me like if I
tell you all the attributes which I mean to
say this all things text password
input radio button drop down
most of them
70-80% of them
comes under only one type of
you know one type of
tag which is input tag
if I type down input tag
and just close it
it's a self closing tag there is nothing
in between you can write
everything that you have just
told me like all the suggestions
that I've got except drop down
I guess except drop down
most of the things can be covered
using input tag is that part
clear at least till now
so input tag is
all the thing that you need
okay now
let's say you have the third thing
is button
inside our button let's say you
have submit okay
this is how our user
like login form looks like right
like you have two things like
you can type it down anything here also
you can type it down anything but
this doesn't
explain us anything like what
this boxes should be filled with
so we should give something naming convention
to it let's say for writing
inside the box right we have
something like a attribute called placeholder
whenever I have user
placeholder I'll say that
username whenever I give that
hey this is username or let's
say please enter or like
leave it that way because we are not using much extra
space let's say name
username again if I define
a placeholder I'll say
that password
okay now
even if I do it this way I am typing
it down it is erasing
right it is erasing can you see this
that still it is erasing but
even then you want to show
that hey even if it is erased
I want to know what you have entered what
I want to remember now let's say there are
20 fields there are
20 fields 20
fields of form you have given place
holder describing what
you have to enter but you have
entered 7 8 fields
and you went for a break you came back and
you see that 7 fields are filled you don't
know what you have filled right because
you don't have anything describing what
this field is associated with isn't
it
do you guys agree
okay for that
we need something which
tells that hey what this particular
field is talking about for that
we need something called as label
okay
when you use label let's say
when I am using a label called
username
okay
when I write username now by
default you will be able to see that hey
this is talking about username
this field let's say I put this inside the
div
such that they are
together okay
now even this
is saying that please enter username or
username even if you type you know that hey this field
is talking about username by default you can say
similarly what I will do
is like I will go with the second part
I will create another div I will pick this
input tag I will
keep it here
and I will also add a label
part for it
which will say password
okay
or capital P
okay now
let's say you also have
a brick which is a line
brick I am using it
okay which will give us space guys
nothing else it's not needed
but you can use using CSS
but I am just using it for namesake
okay let's remove it
we are not introduced it
we won't use it okay
so we see that we have two things
we have defined label now
but still password
we are able to see right there is something
like dotted thing it should be there
but it's not coming up right
for doing that part
you have to use attribute called type
earlier also
for defining different types of
list changing how
enhancing those right type of
list with numbering convention or ABC
or anything we used type
attribute itself here also we will use type
attribute itself with let's say I
say now password when I say password
and I save it
why is this
okay now when I say this as a type
as a password now if you see whenever
I am typing it
okay P A S
okay now
if you see whenever I am typing it
now if you see like I am not
able to see but this is a trick guys
does anyone know
how we can get this password
without you know
person asking that person
let me
from inspect okay I will
open inspect so you guys have to
help me out
how one can do it this is
one of the thing that we used to do in our childhood
but
so some people know it already
like let's say
I typed on user name
okay I also typed
on password
so one thing you can do guys is that
I will go and
select this field particular field
now once I have this type as
password I can change it to text
once I change it to text I can see what
I have typed how many
of you did this with your friends
or your girlfriends or boyfriends
most of them
great
so
okay
I used to
use one of the how can we
add space between the label and input
without CSS
some bit
I actually used a line break
that's not
necessary but we can have
this break okay
okay if you see this I have
a break field
br
which is break the line
okay this is how you can give the space
label and input okay
label and
input okay
give me a second
now for that thing right
always one thing you can do is like you can give
extra space that doesn't work
but without using CSS
without using CSS why
give me a second guys
without using CSS yeah can we
I will think about it currently it is nothing
striking me but we will think about it okay
and Anandu
says something y slash n
this way
is it
I am using for slash yeah
so you know my way of
writing is like when you go for appear coding
right whichever thing you are opening it
please close them
anything that you are opening please close them
okay
so that's why I was using
can we use table so that align properly
we can use it but login forms are
we will take care about styles
later on guys don't worry about styles or the
spaces as of now let's grab the
concept of table okay
now coming back to this
one please give your attention guys
once we complete login form we will take a break
and we will come back okay
how we can align both user and password
box parallel
Sambit we will come back to
styles later okay let's focus on
forms alignment CSS we will think about
later okay
so that the content which we need to cover
we will cover it up today
okay
now
already I think Suresh
has given the answer but we will see
the other things later
guys how many of you remember
one thing that whenever
I click on something like
this field my cursor
takes focus inside
this one like whenever
I click username my focus
goes inside this whenever I click
password my focus goes inside
this
did anyone observe this one
this functionality in forms
like whenever we click on something
on label it
goes inside this let's see if we have
any site which can show us
let's see
scalar.com works or not
incognito will open
incognito because
scalar.com
say okay
this thing has a different naming
you know they have changed
with CSS
or any other website let's say
flip card
sign up
too much responsive
okay they have this simple naming
convention or let's say
material UI
bootstrap
how many of you use bootstrap
earlier
I see some of
the people have used it
so I am checking guys I am not able
to see one thing but
there should be something like
content I am going for forms
so form control
I don't know
good form control but
yeah now if I click a password
now if you guys see this
what I was talking about now I am not
going inside this and typing it
but I am clicking on this
label itself whatever label is there
I am clicking on there it is taking
focus inside so this is what I
was thinking
so anyone any idea how we can do this or
how we can achieve this
bootstrap is something
framework which is
built in components that we can use
we will talk about that
in future upendra
diraj says for in label
so whenever you are
clicking this thing that is taking
focus inside this means there is some
attribute which is enhancing this
functionality right
one thing we have to do is
lets say for the placeholder
I will have an id
now I am using new
attribute
id for any
field or anything that you
define for each html
file it should be unique
try to make it as
much unique as possible like
id stands for unique id
now lets say I give
as user name itself
now this id I will associate
with this label using fur
so whenever I am writing
a fur and I am saying that hey
this particular user name of
label is associated with this id
then I say that whenever this thing happens right
now whenever I click on a user name
my focus automatically goes inside
this user name
now lets say if someone is
connecting with
placeholder
no it doesn't work with a placeholder
it works with id attribute
whenever I am clicking this still it goes inside
is this clear guys how I am able to
go inside clicking on a
user name label inside this
in a same way lets do it
for the password also
now once I
go here I come here
and id I make it as
password
now again I click here
I am having password
now
one thing that
will do it is like now
if I click on a submit button
lets do it on browser
I think we have opened this on browser already
no this is incognito window
lets say this is
where it is
now if you see here
we got the page
from this local server
but lets say I type down
anything
my name and some random
data as password and click on submit
as soon as I click on submit
if you see there is something happening
I am not able
to show it here
give me a second
lets say I make it as submit
once I have this
I actually
wanted to show you how
post data call works
lets see this
after break
once we define
registration then we will go with
how this post data
thing works
now action part I don't want to introduce
that attribute to it
so that changes the url part
so we will see that
what if I add a method
like post
since we know what post method does
lets say I have a post
and I have something
I click here
nothing will happen here
now if you see
it failed to send
405 errors it says
nothing is there
inside this
post method
login form html
lets see this, we will come back and explore this part
use get
get is getting the data
its not something you should use
you should use post method when you are posting
you are also generally posting the data
sending the data
so guys
other than this submit event
which is not part of
discussion as of now
is everyone clear
like how we can define input tag
and how we can play around with user name
password and submit button
and how we are associating
whether it is necessary to give id
100% vigneshwar
if you have any of the usage of id
in future classes
once we will start with css
and even when you go for react
how id matters
but it is surely
if I am your code reviewer
I would ask you to add id for your
whatever
html content
structures you are writing
so
guys if this everything related to
login form is clear
if you want a break we can take a break
or if you want me to go ahead
with registration form I can go ahead
whats your take guys
for attribute value in the label
id value must be same
right yeah for value
attribute and label and id value
must be same yes exactly
break please
ok 10 minutes break for dinner
how many
how to remember valid unique
id for entire site
not necessarily
so now if you say
each form when you define I am saying
login form how many times you will have
user name id
or please enter user name id
you cannot have
more than 2-3 names right
so you
define unique names like
by default because even id
helps you to
write unit test cases
in future we will see in react
because you use the data test id
but I will
talk about that its not about
remembering unique name its just writing it
unique name ok it shows
that why I will tell you
whenever a DOM is built
right whenever a DOM is built
now each thing
now if you see
going back
now
lets say
what happens is if I have
this div two divs are there
if I have this id
we will talk about this in
future
lets take a break from that
we will talk about that in future
you will have many use cases
lets go for the break guys
I will start the timer
please after css
yes yes
so how it will work is that
you will learn
JavaScript after that
you will go for react because react
works with HTML, CSS, JS
you have to have a knowledge on DOM
we will build a project called canban
after that we will go for
react so its project
project driven module mostly
so we will see that and we will learn
and we will go with that
ok how many minutes
guys 10 minutes is too much guys
give me thumbs up for 10 minutes
and thumbs down
for 5 minutes
ok I see
8 and 4
lets say
I will
give it 10 minutes
but if anyone have any
doubts I will solve it right away because
later on the time it goes
too much if anyone want to ask
anything they can ask we can discuss
break is on guys
I am not discussing anything new
I am just discussing whatever content is
discussed till now if you have any doubts
from content till
we have discussed
yesterdays class last class and
todays class you can ask me I will be there
ok
or if you want to add it in the question tag
please add it there but
you can take break guys lets see
meet back in 10 minutes
yeah
that's part of CSS
that you can add it
in CSS part
we will see that how that works and
how you can enhance the input types
all those things can be done using
attributes and CSS but
as of now lets
keep it simple
can you show one label for an ID
ok yeah
sure I will keep that screen share
yeah
so I am using label
for user name and ID is
associated with the same thing
ok
so whenever I am using
user name when this user name
is associated with this
field even if I click on this it
focuses on user name
ok
same for me its not
working
do one thing
kishore can you share me
your code in whatsapp chat or
lets connect in the add out session
ok
we will figure out
refresh the screen and
try once how to remember this
all HTML attribute types an easy
way to remember will all this ask for
interview
so first thing shanth
many a times I dont
remember all of things
interviewer if interviewer
is asking you to
build those forms and types right
you are allowed to google
or you can ask him like if I
can google this I know how we can remember
basically all other input
types you need to
remember categories of it
its not that everything you will google and type
it down ok
attributes or anything
so I too personally dont
remember all of things even if I am
taking any interviews I allow that user
like you can google you can figure it out
because its really difficult
because there is no sense
there is no meaning remembering
all of them because
with one shot of search you will
get it you will be able to build it
its just like mugging up right if you are
remembering there is no
sense
so you should be allowed
like if some
I would say I cannot guarantee
100% on anything but
as for my
idea my knowledge one should be allowed
to you know google it
because this is not something to remember
ok this is not something where
I am testing your IQ or your
coding skills or your knowledge on front end
ok there are many things that I can test on
but not on the HTML part
HTML part they might allow
they should allow you to search if you are
stuck anywhere
yeah understanding depends on person
to person but most of the things
I am trying to make it simple
because even if you see when I was trying
to write about forms I have asked
you like how many types of forms field
can be there and I have told you everything
comes under only input type
now once you have typed on input
and you just give type equal to that particular
field he will know that this guy
knows something but he is trying to figure out some other
part he himself will tell or
he will help you out directly or you can
search ok
on a broader perspective you should understand
things not completely blank will help
you out ok
so anyways I will take
break for 5 minutes and come back ok
thanks for watching
you
ok
guys I hope everyone is back
great
I see three thumbs up maybe a few more people
guys, thumbs up, thumbs down,
if you are back
so we'll get started with you know another login from guys which is
registration form create a file registration form dot HTML let's focus
for some more time guys let's just build this and this is where we'll use most
amount of the you know different HTML tags that of form types okay let's call
this as a registration form okay let me open this and show preview and let me
close this let's keep it this way no inside body again I'll give an header
h2 which talks about again registration form okay now first thing first like
every time whenever you're creating a form you need to have a form element
once you have form defined it inside that you can define define multiple
things now for form what all things you'll have for registration what all
things you'll have like let's say name then let's say you have email then let's
say you also ask persons age then you might ask gender of a person right and
then you might ask date of birth anything else guys anything else address
phone number address phone number right you can ask his photo and then it could
be a submit but right this would be a generic normal form right what wherever
you go and see upload upload file is a photo that's where we'll have all the
types of documents that you can upload so this is what a general form would
look like a recession form where you ask his details and related information and
submit it and where you store it in your DB okay now let's say we'll try to build
and even we'll ask him to give his password right if we are registering
some for him so something last class ask him to give his password right now
let's start building this one by one guys let's start reading this one by one
okay now I'll use div sections for each of this okay now I'll show you a new way
of writing you know this thing where I'll use label inside that I'll say this
is a name and I'll use input here itself inside this okay so that it is on the
side of it like a label then type input now let's say here in the type I'm using
this one as a text okay placeholder would be enter name okay let me okay and
what I'll do is guys I'll minimize this one for some time till we type it down
what we have learned till now okay and let's keep this as simple let's let's
pull this also it down since that is what we have learned till now okay now
for form of a label I'll use this as a name okay let's say user name and ID
would be user name this is same now let's say I copy this and paste it for
here for the email ID okay I say user email let's say user email I copy and
paste it as for ID for means what we are associating with like this label is
associated with each with input with which input item which input element so
IDs are associated on and okay now since this is a email let's say I typed on
email please enter email for now input type right only from text to convert
into email you can use this as a email okay now does anyone know how you can
make a field mandatory how we can make a input field mandatory just by giving
required here you say just required it will like if you go and don't enter it
I'll show when you click submit if you give a required attribute by default it
will become mandatory okay similarly let's build for other things I'll
minimize this one for a second guys until we build this others let me open
this here in the live server okay here we will keep seeing everything
parallely now for going for the password since we have already seen this I'll
define it in same way this is user password password enter password okay
and instead of email I'll say a password okay three things no so if I type down
this way this is working fine till now so here I should be given at the rate
gmail or at the rate it generally checks for at the rate before we are going for
the validation part I'll show you how we can check this but now let's just build
the items okay then if you go for age what should be the age field like how
should you define age what do you think like what should be the type of age
like generally it should be a text or a number or what it should be number
numeric now let's say this let's define it that way again let's take this div
copy and paste it here and let's say user age I'm using user in order to keep
it unique age
age type should be number let's say what is required not mandatory okay if you go
and see I am getting this number okay now let's say whenever we are making
some website which should be like only plus 18 people can see and only below
60 age like we are having a range of people only a load like do you know how
we can restrict that do you know how we can restrict that like what what age
people can be there okay for numeric fields right you have two more attributes
okay min and max so now so let's say I'm giving min as 18 and max as 60 so only
between those age fields you will be able to select like let's say I go here
I start with only 18 there's no no more things are going below or like limit or
a condition you can say and let's say I also have some width here as 100 pixel
don't ask me currently what is pixel or how we are adding up with we'll discuss
this in CSS okay but here it's not getting applied is it
let's say I give it in the style only
no I'm able to keep this it now what I was trying to show is that minimum when
you give you a condition right you will be starting from 18 and then you can go
up to anything like even if I give 64 right when I do it this one this is this
will be this we are setting a condition like if you hover over it right if you
see this value must be it says that less than or equal to 60 can you see
this message coming below here
at here like if I write down 63 and I come down if you if I hover back it shows
that value must be less than or equal to 60 so it shows that validation also it
is it so we have a condition over this counter okay all the values whatever
user entered is you have to validate again before you are sending it to the
server okay now once this age is done let's go for gender now what how you
want to represent gender any suggestions case how we want to represent gender we
have discussed this already using radio buttons now let's see how you can define
radio buttons okay firstly I'll have a label gender a common label then again
to define multiple labels let's say again I have diff inside this we can use also
drop down right we can use Abhinav both things but I'll use radio I'll use
drop down for the other field okay let's say I have label again because for each
input I mean for each radio button you should have label let's say this is male
and once you have male let's say I have an input type again type would be radio
okay and let's say similarly you have
female others let's say this is how this is looking first we are able to get this
under the gender but how do you make this like associate this one again now
we said that radio again this should be male should be associated with let's say
male for male and ID should be male and for should be here again female and here
also I'll use ID as a female okay same I'll use again for attack this is some
I'm not focusing because this is something we have discussed already so
I'm just typing it down guys whatever we have discussed only when there is new
thing I'm talking about that okay now once we have defined ID now let's see
one feature one thing guys one buck now radio button is a feature where you can
select only one thing right you cannot select multiple features right multiple
things when you have a multiple options multi option you have a checkbox sort
of thing but when you have a radio button you can only select one night one
of it right a person cannot be male female and others three altogether right
do you guys agree right now how we can restrict this one how we can restrict
this one that well person can only select one or one item out of this how
we can restrict this one any idea anyone any idea how we can restrict this right
so if you keep common name right name is attribute I'll talk about this how name
works give me a second I'll let's say this is talking about gender I'll keep
it here common name for all of them okay and let me give it value also okay let
this is male
it's a female so it should be okay now let's see if this is working first
using name when I click this then I'm able if I'm able to click this if I'm
if I'm clicking this this is being removed now right this is working as
expected now user is only able to select one among three right either he is male
or female or others right how we did this because we added a same name now
why we are adding a same name is because a person can be only one type and via
how how name attribute can be used as whenever you are submitting a form right
whenever form is submitted usually form contains a data like this right is gender
what is his gender okay either is male or female you will select it this way
now how where this value will be coming from okay where this male value or female
value or other value will be coming from is whatever value you define inside the
value attribute that will be sent when you click on a submit button from the
form element is this clear guys how name and value are associated
does all of you understand how name and value is associated guys a few more
thumbs up if you are again please write something okay so now whichever field
you are selecting or you are selecting or anything you are typing it down or
when it comes to selection of this type right male female or others now
whenever you are selecting one thing how we should know that what it is
selected I see value and ID I didn't I don't understand value and ID I see
value and ID is different but still works for other no please I didn't
understand your question again other and others yeah yeah see this ID is
different IDs are like just to be unique among the for each attribute okay
for this label I am using this ID but here name and gender why why sorry name
and value when where I'm using is that for each input form right each other
form so value can be anything value is something user will be typing it now
whatever value you type it down that is what you are sending back to the server
right now if if if I'm having this radio button right if I'm forgiven a user a
gender or the text box he would be either writing male female or other if
you are giving them already like check radio button the value can be either
male female or other only right it cannot be nothing it cannot be anything
it is what whatever user is selecting if we're selecting this other radio button
by default we will be sending to the server as other is this clear guys how
name and value key are associated
okay still anyone having any doubts
if anyone is still having I'll pick it up in doubt session can anyone explain
can you explain again age again how is that number or appears okay nice going
back to the age part what I was doing here in the age part so I gave type as
a number I've told that hey minimum and maximum like when I've say that minimum
maximum I'm actually giving it to this field like if I start generally let's
say I remove this minimum maximum I comment on these two things or let's say
I cut them and I say I go back here if you see I'm starting from 1 2 3 okay but
now if I have this min and max the counter is starting from 18 to 60 it
will go till 60 okay that's how your condition you are restricting it but if
you are what I was saying is that there's another feature what this shows
is like when you add 65 right whenever you are trying to increase it it will
also hover you like that message like a value must be less than or equal to 60
that was I was talking about but at runtime before sending it to server you
have to through validation arrow comes in the toggle my question is how arrow
other this one this arrow generally type equal to number yeah by default this is
a type
like for radio button when we say type radio this you can see the circles by
default it comes that way okay how button is selected now let's say if I go
for this one guys now let's see I expand this one gender right okay now let's say
I selected male now whenever I'm going to female now if you see here this all
the names right firstly how do you think that this form data value of gender
should be stored value of gender should be stored it should be this way only
right like how would you do it it would be gender colon male or female or
others right only three possible things now so we are storing only one person
gender so I'm saying that all these three inputs will have only one name
okay we'll have only one name now so if you are selecting one value and then
you are selecting another value so it will override that selection it is just
like you type down one password email and you remove that email again and you
type down something new so it is selecting new value is that clear upendra
that's how behavior works name act like a variable huh name act like a variable
the container name like what is the container name like that that's how it
works okay let's let's move it guys let's move it we have too many things to
define for going for date of birth again I will pick it up this one let's say I
have user DOB date of birth once I have here for date of birth type would be
date okay then ID would be this one enter date of birth and in date of birth
also you have one ability like you can give a min date and maximum date okay
let's say type was okay D O P okay
I so user
okay here in date of birth also you have an ability to give users like minimum
date and maximum date okay let's let's before that let's remove this and let's
see this calendar okay once like how this calendar comes up now if you see
here in the date of birth once I define type equal to date okay you see you can
see this calendar you can go to any year and you can select anything that you
want okay but what if we want to restrict something what if we want to
restrict something how we can do that for this one also you have same thing as
min and max let's say I give min value as 20 23 let's say 11th month which is
this November to 10th date like to then maximum maximum would be like you are
limiting the range of a user like how from when to when like let's say to well
let's say 10 so what we did is we gave only 10 month there like one month
validity okay let's say if I go back in the calendar if you see by default I I
cannot go and select other years like the fields are disabled okay if I can go
back into 2023 I have November and December on even if in November since I
start from 10th date I cannot select any other date okay I can select this one or
if I go down I can go up to 10th maximum December is this clear how this works
how we can minimum I put a condition on this one right let me use this width
since date is not completely visible okay end date don't go beyond current
date as a but that is that is okay that that by default you can write down the
logic for that one okay like even if I even if I remove that max date right
even if I remove that max let's say minimum date is fixed what is what
maximum date how it takes okay I go I can go back if you see I'm today on 4th
but I can still give 5th date so type date gives an ability that you can keep
you can select any date but when you give min and max it restricts that if
you don't give me a max it is open ended it can go up to anything okay okay the
format here let's say I I gave in DD year month and date as of now this is in
format of yyy mm and DD but let's change this and let's see this 10 11 20 23 okay
how's this is perceiving okay so now if you see it didn't took in that format so
the right format of giving this ways and reverse format itself like I'll undo so
this is how it takes it okay there is you I I even don't remember some formats
it's just that you do it mistake and then you correct back okay no so I hope
date is clear moving it but the other part let's say I go for the address okay
let's say user address address now what would be the type for address guys any
suggestions
so text but do you think text can be user address will be only one-liner
address can be of multi lines right or like five six lines where you enter a
paragraph type so for them right you have some component called component
text area type which allows you to write multi-line comments like let's say here
if I type down let me go back text area
give me a second
why this didn't work
sorry it doesn't have an input element but by default you have to define text
area so these are the things guys only few things which needed a different
element like other than input let's say this is the one of the element that I
have text area it's also open and close brace here let's say I have a place
holder user address and I can have an ID associated with user address okay now if
you go back and if you see this address right you have here extension you can
extend till how many lines you want how many ever you wanted so there's like
there is no restriction but you can also give many attributes to it like you can
define like what are the like if you go and open the text area right in MDN
field open let's say if you see here rows and columns if you say let's say
if we define this rows and columns as 3 5 and 33 what happens okay so by default
this is given this much space okay if we edit this let's say if we go and edit
this I am using element selector I go here I say reduce this column by 33 32
let's say 10 if you see the column size is got reduced completely so now you
understand it how this rows and columns works and how you can play around with
the text area if you need it wherever you have multi-line comment like address
fields you can use a text area part is text area clear guys how we can enable
spell checker for this type of input spell checker how can we put address
word in middle hey CSS work will check it in later part spell checker is
something we cannot do it that needs actually a dictionary right because we
are validating every word that the type whether it is right in spelling or wrong
it so this by default we don't have any dictionary as of now so it's an
external thing that you have to integrate with who you spell checker okay
right because it's users in area how users can make mistake if you want to
automate that that's a really great thing if you build that even spell
checkers that app will be store sold for a good amount of money if you can build
that which can validate user spelling with less amount of time again now
coming back to phone number let's just build this phone number again let's have
dev label phone number and then again have a input tag for phone number you
have type equal to phone itself once you have type equal to phone and ID could be
user phone number let's say I go here for the user phone number okay now let's
go and see how this works if you see here I am having this phone number type
here generally what happens is whenever you have type right each phone number by
default it's not available you have to use number itself what happens with
phone number is people use custom build like you generally see country code
right one is plus nine one or zero zero or anything so they have one drop down
and then they have like numbers okay maximum numbers limit you can add we can
only allow integers like you know if you only write numbers like you I'm trying
to type down something alphabets I'm not able to but I can write down numbers as
many as I can okay so that's how you can use it for phone numbers like type
number now let's go for photo how you can use for photo please select upload
your profile photo profile picture let's say user profile pic I copy and paste it
here then this is input type of file so whenever you give type file it will go
there and you see here you will get a choose a file okay if I click this file
choose a file it will open you know file system actually like when I click this I
don't open that okay but this is how we can upload it we can limit a phone
number up to ten digits yes you can do that yes you can do that let's say you
I'll go and open this input type number you can go here and we can search this
okay if you see here these are the list of things that are available you have
input mode numeric you can also give the pattern rejects or what all things they
can enter but I will show you how we can use that we can use phone instead of
number right a phone doesn't exist I guess input type phone so it is like
tell tell is something used for phone number let's say I replace this with
okay let's go back and see this if this is there see it tell doesn't work guys
also I have to give the pattern then only it will work but keeping it a simple
as of now we'll see how we can develop the phone number phone number is
actually filled with two drop down or one drop down which selects a country
code plus nine one or anything like for India then other fields are like having
a text number where you can have a validations on each form you can have a
multiple validations I will see how we can add validations in the future
classes this is just an introduction part not completely ending with this
because we'll go in depth one by one in future classes okay when we build
projects
plus nine one drop down shant that is where you'll get those drop downs right
but if you want to get the country code like all plus nine one everything
someone should be there to supply you all the drop down values or you have to
do it manually if you are doing it in HTM okay now we have covered everything
let's say for a drop down right let's say I have a drop down value as a degree
let's say what is a user degree let's add somewhere in this between I didn't
have select field so I add off before on the top of this one now I have a dip
section I have a label section I say select your degree okay once you go for
select your degree what we can do is that for only two things as of now we
have seen other than input like one is text area the second thing is select
only two places we are using other than input tag this these are the two taxes
of now order of all the types that we have chosen okay so it's purely simple
whenever you're going for forms most of them are built using input tag itself
now when you go for a drop down you say that hey please select among the least
of values now each least of value is generally called as a draw option okay
when you go for here so you have to give options okay inside this option let's
say you have B tech any else to any other degree guys anyone having my fire
thing BSE is their computer science master of computer science again any
other degrees holders not less other than beating BA of any other guys MCA
okay MBA okay MBA MCA MCA is also there no masters so that way then I should go
for M tech also
BSE MSC
Mbps why would Mbps be in here he would be earning more than us one surgery he
would we should be go for surgeon M tech let's say okay now so wherever you if
you see this right can we have nested drop down that is custom component of
you know that is custom component yeah okay thank you got it okay let's say a
value whenever you are building something where user is selecting but
you are not allowing user to add anything manually there you have to have
this value define what this field is like associated with like or what is
actually value of this one okay I'm having value for multiple things here
let's say a BA
MBA
MSC then let's say value M tech then lastly I have submit button
for submit also you have a type attribute which talks about what type of
buttons is separate okay now so these are the things that we have introduced
today like you know if you go for degree right now if you see I have BSE BA MBA
all the things that you can select okay now let's say you type it down all the
things it's a phone number is this one then you select some random date mail
ages 23 email is some random thing password is also random I'm just
selecting if I click submit if I have to see now there's a one validation race if
you see this validation I haven't introduced anything but can you see on
script please include at the rate in the email address now if I add just at the
rate right take it at the rate and gmail.com that validation will go down
this is coming from a HTML tag itself when we use red red email okay now if I
submit it one thing is here happening one one only one thing is happening
which is I want to show you something is that we added like let's say I have one
thing I want to show you all is that okay let's say I show it in the login
form itself this is too useful but I'll show what happened here if you see in
the URL right gender mail got appended where this where this thing how this
thing got appended anyone any idea how did we got this mail gender mail in the
URL
name attribute because we have given a name attribute to it now let's go to
login form let's do one thing let's do one thing let's go to login form since
it's a really small thing but before that is everyone clear about this type
of fields how we are adding it how we are creating all this type of forms clear
right now let's go back to login form now here we didn't had anything name yet
here let's say I have a name I say user name here and for the password also I
have a password as me okay once we add this now let's go back to the login form
and have some random username some random password once I click submit if
you see for this one actually I'm sending in the payload now if you see
how did we got this username and password because we we told that hey
these are the two input fields whenever we are making an API call let's say now
we made an API call to the post method also I'll introduce some action method
please don't take it this one this is a next level thing we'll discuss this
how we are redirecting to a new page or making an API call how this thing works
okay just I'll do something is like slash sign in okay nothing nothing much
more specific here what I what will happen let's see what what will happen
now going back to our site okay I'll have let's say username and random
password name once I click this submit now if you see in a header it's showing
post method but it is not showing the URL change okay we'll see about this
action just a second type of button submit let's say we don't want it to
submit let's keep it this way since it's changing the two new path still it is
sending it anyways so let's remove this method post as of now I want to show you
the just in the URL part also I've shown there going back still does it send it
or append it okay 405 okay anyways guys so what I was talking about is like how
how you can fill the data from the form and how we can send back to the server
now whenever you are adding any type of input tag or any input tag which you
need when you're collecting data from the user right you are collecting in
terms of this name tags like every data that you store let's say you have
multiple things name password okay if you want to send this email ID right if
you are sending this user information and you have this key rice out of this
map whatever keys you have that should be say that should be defined here in
the name attribute is that clear is what name attribute is about that is where we
are also using in the gender part like in even if you go for gender part or any
place that if you if you go and see let's say I have here added multiple
things you can try it out on this registration form offline like adding
names and trying to submit this form okay
so so guys any doubts in the forms as of now just talk about tags and other
things nothing about like as of now related to methods or action things that
we haven't introduced yet or how we deal with them we'll talk them about in the
future classes when you are actually having sending the data to the server or
when you're collecting data from you know from the user and actually playing
around in the full stack application okay why value attribute specifically in
the drop-down okay now not in specifically in the drop-down but we
also used for the gender if you see here in the gender I've used value attribute
now all the user entered input right user entered input whenever user is
having ability to enter input value will be automatically given by the user but
when you're giving a drop-down or a radio button type of field right then you
don't have that user will not give any value he'll be selecting itself so what
I am saying is that if he's selecting mail now if he's selecting this input
type send value as male if he's selecting this thing send value as female
okay even in the drop-down if he's selecting BTEC as a drop-down value send
this BTEC as a value is this clear Suresh and the name would be here like
degree
did you understand this user Suresh got it right fine now there's one thing that
I forgot to add it is this one remember me checkbox since we didn't introduce
checkbox I'll just add its placeholder we don't need a placeholder here type
type
checkbox an ID would be remember me okay now once you have an checkbox then you
have to also have a label remember now let's see how this looks yeah this is
how it looks remember me on off no even if I send this data if you see when I'm
sending this sign in this is how data will be sent in like username password
now remember me this thing is coming again from the name field which is name
field this name field so I hope name value type attributes input type how
labels are associated with you know input type so I hope you got all this
basics clear guys yeah there is a value will be defined by us or a developer
wherever user doesn't have an ability to submit it we will be giving them
options right so wherever you select an option we have to define what type of
value we have to keep it I mean serving the server back end okay so guys there's
one topic left actually I have to cover it do you want me to cover it today or
want me to take it in the next class
in the next class there's just a inline inline versus okay let's say there's a
only small thing I have to say talk about inline versus block dot HTML let's
say HTML 5 now what happens with inline is that let's say I have div
okay now I'm writing inside this as text let's say text let me open in the show
preview okay I'm having text now let's say I'm also having another text one
let's say next thing I'm having a span tag okay text 2 then again I'm having a
span tag text 3 now do you see any difference in this case do you see any
difference what is the difference between this
this is just a one-liner you know thing that will cover it up then again this
will will see this in the again CSS classes span is coming side by side div
is taking next line that is only the thing guys that is it that is it so in
line elements
takes only the amount of space needed okay so when I say inline element the
example for inline element is span so text 2 needed only this amount of space
it took then if you add another span it it will go into text to line this line
itself because this has this amount of space right empty space but when it
comes to block level elements
always starts in new line okay because div is an example for block level
that's the reason why we say that div is used for sections different type of
section I want of space okay generally and there are many examples for this
one let's say I go with hyperlink anchor type so anyone want to do like
let's say I I'll do it since we are having a less amount of time left let's
say I have href www.google.com okay let's say this is Google site let's say I
also have
Facebook Facebook is rare now or people are moved to Instagram right can you
see a behavior of anchor tag now you have to say what type of element is
anchor tag inline right
okay so anchor tax are also example of inline elements now let's say let's
think of image okay image now let's I define it here in the image okay image
let's say I give some random information okay now I added this thing
let's say I give another image now can you see image is also coming in the same
line if image is also being placed in same line so that is also inline tag
because it takes only the amount of space it is needed it doesn't take it
always doesn't start on newlet whereas div is someone who always start on a new
line okay that's the basic code difference between inline versus block
elements okay now if you want me to give for a few more examples of block element
let's say I go with paragraph okay I'm typing only four five letters okay now
again I have a new paragraph now I am typing it you so paragraph after this
thing right there is too much amount of space available in that row in that row
but it is when I'm introducing new paragraph it is starting in the new
line right so whenever there is a some element which always starts in new line
are block level elements but whenever there is an HTML element which takes
only the amount of space it needed and allows the next element to start from
there itself that is called inline element is that clear guys so I've given
few examples of type of elements HTML elements what are like inline or just
block hope this this is just an introduction we'll see like how we can
convert an inline element into block block into inline in CSS because we'll
play around with them for the introduction part let's keep it this
much because if you go in depth right there's nothing to go in depth just just
a definition level in elements takes only the amount of space needed allows
the next element let's say after this span also text is rewrite even if I give
diff even if I give diff I say some random it will always start a new line
because this person doesn't care if there is extra space he says that I am
special I'll come on the new line only
okay so would you remember what is inline versus block because we'll
revisit this topic in next class or the other further classes so let's keep it
this much guys for today let's keep it this much and we'll see like how we can
cover portfolio part okay portfolio project whenever we are having some
time we'll build it together okay okay so a with your permission can I start
doubt session because this is what the content I wanted to discuss today
so nice nice so starting this doubt session guys give me a second okay so
I've started doubt session guys whoever have doubts right please stay in the
call or it's others feel free to drop but one thing I want to say is that you
know in self-study right I have added few links okay you can go to open preview
whenever okay whenever you want to like whatever links I'll be adding you can
refer it directly you click on HTML reference material it will navigate to
new site I will show you the site how it works it navigated to different page okay
this was a site that I was referring to this is like web def which will help you
to you know go with all the things it's just like if you want to read through
right all the semantic elements metadata attributes what are the types of
different attributes links least navigation table forms all the things
that we discussed are there still even the advanced level items are there like
audio and video how you can connect with audio and video okay we'll see example
by example how we can take it but this is a plain HTML5 content not completely
in depth because MDN is someone who maintains that Mozilla this MDN site
you can refer to this one which have completely in depth but I don't prefer
you reading through this one because it's it's there way of writing is not
that up to an extent I mean I don't feel comfortable reading them but this is a
better site okay that you can refer to for studying the HTML part or referring
in future even whenever you want to refer anything any attribute or anything
go to this site let's say if you go for forms right let's say you go for form
you will able to see that what is our difference between input type submit and
the button type submit okay so all the things right forms we have seen just now
like form label now if you see first student is connected with ID student and
name they have given for select and values they have given for these
elements okay options and they have given input type submit event okay now
if you see this is something you can change it okay so all the elements will
be there here which you can go through and understand in depth if you want to
skim through it like like skim through it like when I say skim through it like
just like revise it go to this repo open this particular class because what I am
doing is like I'm maintaining another readme MD where which will show that
what topics were covered in which class okay so if you want to go through any
topic let's say you want to revise forms you go to the class to expand it you
will be able to see in that okay so how to access this give me a second I'll
give you the github repo I I have already added in the whatsapp group I
pinned it but I'll also pin here give me a second so this is a site guys I mean
get I'm maintaining a github repo for this one now one thing one of the hack
is like always convert into their format which is online you know convert into
visual studio code if you want to go through and read some down someday okay
or you want to open it in editor format okay so you can expand it you can go
through it open preview okay if you don't want to open it in please share
the whatsapp link okay give me a second hey anyone I'll pin it here give me a
second I'll open it I'll pin on this one also let's say I convert into calm
again so one can go through this readme and also self study right if you expand
the cell study there is a link dot empty if you have you'll have this links you
can open one by one yesterday also we have understood how internet works so
you can go to this site which will explain in short which is scalar topic
site itself but which is explained in short and there are some FAQs also okay
in simple terms give me a minute I'll pull what's up should I have multiple
batches so I'll take this one
invite group link copy link so I'll pin this case thank you shant for pinning
this I'm pin this then let me pin back this one also kitab repo for your access
case okay no so one minute I'll push the code base then I'll take that out
okay terminal so we have also covered in line versus block level elements so if
you have any suggestions for me also you can guys you can share with me
directly also you can write it down there I'll work on that or if you have
anything you can say to indirectly add that also work get add dot get status
get commit minus and then class two
good push so you should be having all the content guys whatever we have done
today okay so this is how you are contable of content would look like like
which class what we have discussed so I'm still working on it to make it much
better if anyone want to contribute they can also contribute taking that kitab
repo and teach kit upcoming classes some bit there is nothing in curriculum as
such but I'll ask if we can add or get videos for our batch okay so that you
can go through and learn okay record I can give you recordings because our
classes are I mean 50 classes for full stack if I take more right then it would
be like extending that weeks that wouldn't be good okay yeah well I'll ask
and I'll keep you updated related to get get videos okay and second thing yeah
I'll try to share recordings I look at it I read into your archive section so
I'll go to the doubts anyone having any doubts guys I have to scroll up I only
demand span tags do we have any tags other tags
somebody that was yard out itself you push you ping me personally values are
the unique how to restrict some file upload types yeah Suresh let's say this
okay for file upload right input type you can always give what are the amount
of types that you accept okay but you can you you you have to say that input
type file if you go here right in MDN docs or anywhere I'll show you how we
can add here it is not available let's go for the MDN itself so if you see here
you can give what are the accept types of images or the files like image slash
PNG image slash JPEG or else you can give other types also where you have the
scene accept docs doc doc X XML MS word VND so this is like you restricting in a
way is that or what are types of you are accepting you have to tell that but you
cannot say that I don't want to accept this one okay it's a reverse of what
you're asking so there's an accept attribute which which you can use to
deal with this one okay
anything else yes anything else there are too many things as to remember right
even if you see it tell is there which which is talking about phone number type
but you have to give a pattern along with that we'll explore this if needed
in future but it's just that if you know one basic item right how things works
how attributes are associated you will be able to go and explore in the world
like like everything like search is there type search now I haven't covered
this search but you can go and explore and understand there's nothing new here
only the type of attribute search is changed now there can be in future HTML
6 but do you need to upscale again yourself no they might add the same
same sort of things with a new extra types right now when someone asked me
what is bootstrap now when I'm saying that hey I'm not building this right
search box or the search keyword but I'm giving this type equal to search I'm
getting ran defined by default like this is something popping for me so if you
want to pop many other components right like all different things you can use
bootstrap framework which will help you to you know develop its faster rate like
you can use the different components here like will come to grid and
everything later but let's say drop down like if you see but mostly things are
the same like if you see still here there also what they give is like CSS
classes bootstrap generally allows you to write in a better way like if you
see it's a curved right curve type and other things like form select
specifically this select form select group or else like if you say form
select form select hyphen large and mp3 we'll see this once you cover CSS right
you will understand how this bootstrap also working I'll just give you an
overview but not in depth because we'll leverage other frameworks front end is
like too much use guys too much use too much use to cover everything in industry
but once we have correct basics right you will be having enough knowledge to
go and explore and learn okay
yeah some values are something let's say you are collecting from form now once
you collect from the form what you would do you want to send to the server and
database right if I registering a block or doing a login you want to store that
data whatever user is entering on submit you want to send to the server so
whenever you want to do this you will of course store it in some key value pairs
right what this value that user has entered for this particular input field
now the what has he entered for this field that key name itself so okay so
with name itself yeah it is a key value pair name whatever you define it in name
right whatever you define it in name that will become key and whatever user
is entered that will become value okay
so guys if all doubts are resolved can we end the session today it's thank you
Shan there's a lot lot to learn so hope you know you keep on doing assignments
like everything will be done in the next session so thank you so much for watching
you keep on doing assignments like everything will be really like once I
once you leave an assignment two days or three days you keep cap right it would be
a lot to cover that's why I'm worried about that I'm running back of you that
hey keep doing it because this is my against a second and a half batch I know
how things can be difficult for the future time for your guys so I would
ask you to keep on hands-on because you're learning too much just go through
the notes that's the reason why I'm putting extra words sharing with you
whatever possible I can do from I say so that you can refer because the revision
of this full stack will be difficult when you go for context like mock
interviews that's why I'm preparing all the things that hey you need anything
just go to get up report you'll have everything okay so just keep doing
assignments and keep me if you want anything help from me tag me in the
WhatsApp group I'll try to pitch in from my side okay so thank you guys thank you
for attending today's session hope you have a great night and see you in the
Saturday class hopefully I expect all the people who were today present in the
class to come on the Saturday to don't skip Saturday class which is a basic
where we'll start again on Saturday css1
yeah thank you some with even I felt like kept kept on speaking I'll have a
water and then something after nice so guys and see you see you in the next
session thank you all good night guys good night take care
you